Welcome to MuseScore in Minutes
A series of short videos that will quickly
get you up and running with MuseScore 2.0
I'm Dr. George Hess and in each of
these videos we will look at how to use
some of the basic functions of the
exciting new version of this program
MuseScore is a free and open source
music notation program
that's a great alternative to Finale and Sibelius
You can download it for free
at the website shown on the screen
Lesson 4: MIDI Keyboard Input
In the last lesson we covered basic note input
using only the mouse and computer keyboard
This is fine, particularly when you are away
from your workstation
But there are better ways to enter notes
The first one we'll look at is using a MIDI keyboard
This time we'll start by creating a new score
and using the Jazz lead sheet template
We'll scroll down here and select the template
select our key, our pickup measure
Now let's go ahead
and shorten this a bit to 13 measures
then click finish
Before we get started
we need to open up the preferences
and make sure your MIDI keyboard
is selected as the input device
Preferences are found under the Edit menu
if you are on Windows
Select the I/O tab and then next to MIDI input,
make sure your MIDI keyboard is selected
If not, select it from the drop down menu
and then click OK
And you'll need it then to restart MuseScore
It's ok, we'll wait
This note input method is basically the same
as with the virtual keyboard
You'll choose the note value,
play the note on the MIDI keyboard
Remember the shortcuts
4 for an eighth note, 5 for a quarter,
6 for a half and 7 for a whole
a period for a dotted note and Shift + for a tie
Remember to add the dot after entering the note value
and to select the trailing note value
before entering the tie
So now let's enter the first phrase
First thing we need to do is split that rest
so we'll type 4 to split it
and then the arrow key to select it
Now we'll type N for note input entry mode
and we're ready to play
Type my half note before I type the tie
And add the dot before I enter the note
Now that didn't take long
For most people this method will be the fastest
and feel the most comfortable
In the next lesson we'll look at a couple of ways
to quickly finish our melody